A Guide to the Ernst Friedheim papers, Rockefeller University Faculty FA1107
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ernst Friedheim papers, Rockefeller University Faculty
ca. 1955-1989
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller University.
Friedheim, Ernst A.H., Dr.
FA1107
121.2 Cubic Feet
101 record storage cartons.
Biographical / Historical
Ernst A.H. Friedheim (1900-1989) was a visiting professor of parisitology at the Rockefeller University from 1978-1989. In 1930, he worked with Lenor Michaelis in his biophysics laboratory.
Dr. Friedheim was perhaps best known for his development of melarsoprol, an effective drug for the treatment of trypanosomiasis (African sleeping sickness). He later conducted research on chelating drugs for the treatment of poisoning by heavy metals. This work led Dr. Friedheim to study the accumulations of arsenicals by tumors with the intent of exploiting this phenomenon both for radiodiagnosis and therapy.
Born in Zurich, Switzerland, Friedheim earned degrees in Europe in a number of fields: in medicine from the University of Zurich, in microbiology from the Pasteur Institute in Paris, in tropical medicine and hygiene from the University of Hamburg, and in chemistry from the University of Geneva. He also studied at the Max Planck Institute in Berlin and the Institut d'Optique in Paris.
Dr. Friedheim conducted work in tropical and subtropical regions of four continents, under various government auspices. He was also an advisor to the World Health Organization (WHO).
Scope and Contents
Includes administrative files, articles, correspondence, grant proposals and contracts, laboratory notebooks, memoranda, photographs, reports, reprints, and subject files.
Conditions Governing Access note
The Friedheim films are open for scholarly research. The paper collection remains closed to scholarly research pending further processing. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of the RAC.
All inquiries to view films require advanced notice of at least 48 business hours, and may necessitate notice of up to one week. Individual items, including those that are not available in modern formats, may require creation of an access surrogate. Applicable charges will apply.
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 450 F913-U
- Ernst Friedheim films, 1940-1960; 1; 21 film reels The Ernst Friedheim films contains 21 reels of films including negatives and prints in 16mm format.; The Ernst Friedheim films contains 21 reels of films including negatives and prints in 16mm format.
  Arrangement
  Alphabetical.
  Conditions Governing Access
  When requesting to view audiovisual material, please refer to the Title and the AV Number (example: AV 1916). Researchers are asked to check the "Restrictions" note for each Title. If a Title does not currently have an access copy, please contact a RAC archivist for further instruction.
  All inquiries to view films require advanced notice of at least 2 business days, and may necessitate notice of up to one week. Individual items, including those that are not available in modern formats, may be restricted from access at the discretion of RAC.
  Scope and Contents
  The Ernst Friedheim films document the field research of Ernst Friedheim's African sleeping sickness (African trypanosomiasis) studies in Africa including the Ivory Coast and Benin. The documentary footage highlight the field application of medicine, mobile medical clinics in rural communities, cases of African sleeping sickness infection and effects on the community.
  Documentary films -- Africa; African trypanosomiasis; Public health
  - Ernst Friedheim - Film I: Abomey: Tambour, Variole, Lamhara (Tojo), 1948; Silent, Color, 12 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 2358)
    Access copy currently unavailable. Please contact an RAC archivist for further instruction.
    Footage of Abomey, a city in Benin, and Lamhara, a small town/rural commune in the Taroudant Province of Souss-Massa region of Morocco. Film includes scenes of dances around a cyclindrical structure (tambour) with costumes and short sticks, close up of cyclindrical structure (tambour) with animals on the slide, shots of musicans with their various drums, closeup of dancers as they chat and move about, three women start a new dance, a procession of African individuals with elaborate dress and headdress, and showing a dance on the road.
  - Ernst Friedheim - Film II: Niamcy, 1955; Silent, Color; 16mm film (Reel AV 2359)
  - Ernst Friedheim - Film III: Natitingou / JombreII / Boukonible, 1948-1955; Silent, Tinting/Toning; 16mm film (Reel AV 2360)
    Scenes of Natitinguo a city/commune in northwest Benin.
  - Ernst Friedheim - Film IV A: Begulhie, 1950; Silent, Black and white, 6 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 2361)
    Scenes of male toddlers, children and adults posing for the camera to show skin bateria/rash/condition/deformities (possible sleeping sickness); map of Beoumie; close up of skin condition; interior of medical clinic.
  - Ernst Friedheim - Film IV B: Begulhie / Kenco 933 Africa, 1950; Silent, Black and white, 10 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 2362)
    Scenes of male toddlers and adults posing for the camera to show skin bacteria/rash/condition/deformities (possible sleeping sickness); close up of skin conditions.
  - Ernst Friedheim - Film V: Bougeriba Tamara, 1955; Silent, Color, 7 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 2363)
    Scenes of village with huts, footage of the outskirts of the village, children acknowledge the camera, overlook of the village and brick architecture, cooking rice, footage of 2/3 storied brick huts, a man practices weaving, footage of village tending livestock and animals, and two boys gather water from the ground.
  - Ernst Friedheim - Film VI: Abomey Ballet Konjo Tombes, 1947-1948; Silent, Color, 10 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 2364)
    Scenes of villagers dancing in a long line, a group sit in the middle while the dancing line continues around in a circle, clapping of hands and knees is involved, the musicans show off their drums, select group of women wear the same white garmet as they dance, a brief section of an indoor celebration, travelers arrive by boat and footage of the jungle and rivers.
  - ERNST FRIEDHEIM VII (BRAZIL), 1952; Silent, Color. Film is buckling due to high shrinkage. Do not project.; 16mm, Acetate, print. (Reel AV 2365)
    All inquires to view films require advanced notice of at least 24 hours, and may necessitate notice of up to one week. Individual items, including those not available in modern formats, may be restricted from scholarly access at the discretion of RAC.
  - ERNST FRIEDHEIM VIII (KENCO 942), 1953; Silent, Black & White, 6 minutes. Condition is Good. Safe to project.; 16mm, Acetate, print, 231 feet. (Reel AV 2366)
    Scenes of sleeping sickness in Tanguietta, Northern Dahomey; definition of sleeping sickness title card; a young female shows the progression of the effect of her medication; patient is now pregnant and healthy; a celebration with dance occurs. Copy of AV 2368
  - ERNST FRIEDHEIM IX (NIAMCY MACARTA), 1955; Silent, Black & White/Color. Condition is poor. Do not project.; 16mm, Acetate, Kodachrome. (Reel AV 2367)
  - ERNST FRIEDHEIM X (TAN), 1950; Silent, Black & White, 6 minutes. Condition is okay. Safe to project.; 16mm, Acetate, print. (Reel AV 2368)
    Scenes of sleeping sickness in Tanguietta, Northern Dahomey; definition of sleeping sickness title card; a young female shows the progression of the effect of her medication; patient is now pregnant and healthy and a celebration with dance occurs. Copy of AV 2366
  - ERNST FRIEDHEIM XI (GLOC NOUJOA RDA), 1947; Silent, Black & White/Color. Condition is poor. Do not project.; 16mm, Acetate, print, Kodachrome stock changes to non-Kodachrome. (Reel AV 2369)
    Scenes of the jungle road that villagers walk on, mountain in the background, and brief color stock.
  - Ernst Friedheim - Film XII: Yaws Campaign at Beomie, Ivory Coast, 1950; Silent, Black and white, 8 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 2370)
    Scenes of villagers coming/going to market and treatment center; title card about the application of medicine to remove spirochetes; medicine is administered orally; outdoor medical clinic; parents help the toddlers at the clinic; and the clinic travels to other villages.
  - ERNST FRIEDHEIM XIII (LAMAKARA - TENKEDOYM -BIJJAO), 1947-1949; Silent, Black & White. Due to high shrinkage, do not project.; 16mm, Acetate, print. (Reel AV 2371)
  - ERNST FRIEDHEIM XIV (BOLO JUNAL), 1947-1955; Silent, Black & White. Film is buckling due to high shrinkage. Do not project.; 16mm, Acetate, print, Kodachrome. (Reel AV 2372)
  - ERNST FRIEDHEIM XV (NATITINGOU/JOMBRE I), 1947-1955; Silent, Black & White/Color. Film is buckling due to high shrinkage. Do not project.; 16mm, Acetate, print, Kodachrome, film stock alters throughout reel. (Reel AV 2373)
  - ERNST FRIEDHEIM XVII, 1948-1955; Silent, Black & White/Color. Due to high shrinkage, do not project.; 16mm, Acetate, print. (Reel AV 2375)
  - ERNST FRIEDHEIM XIX (DR. FRIEDHEIM - AFRICA / RAPID TREATMENT OF AFRICAN SLEEPING SICKNESS WITH MEL-B), 1950; Silent, Black & White, 24 minutes. Condition is okay. Safe to project.; 16mm, Acetate, negative, A-wind, 885 feet. (Reel AV 2377)
    Footage of how to treat sleeping sickness. A child being prepared for treatment, his blood is drawn and an injection is given on the second day. Day four of treatment is used for regaining energy and exercising. Villagers line up for medical inspections, medical vaccination is given to villlagers, footage of children crying while taking the medicine orally. An interview with a female villager about the progression of her health. Villagers are dancing now that they are healthy.
  - ERNST FRIEDHEIM XX (KENCO 933 - AFRICA), 1957; Silent, Black & White, 16 minutes. Condition is good. Safe to project.; 16mm, Acetate, negative, 593 feet. (Reel AV 2378)
    Footage of toddlers displaying, for the camera, the different skin diseases and infections; map of Beoumi; older children displaying skin conditions; footage of medical clinic; adults modeling skin conditions.